somebody were to ask me who I thought
were the two most important philosophers
of the 20th century it may
seem like a difficult task to identify
them we have many to choose from people
like Dewey and Pierce Ludwig
Wittgenstein AJ air Anthony flew Merlot
Ponte Herbert Marcus and a host of
others but I for me it's a no-brainer I
think that the two most influential and
important philosophers of the 20th
century are Jean-Paul sarte and Martin
Heidegger
sort of course being French and high
dagger being German
and both of them are associated with the
broad School of existentialism though
Heidegger and sart them both studied
under the same Professor Edmund hussaro
who was the leading voice in his day of
the philosophy of phenomenology and
sometimes technically people will
distinguish between existentialism and
phenomenology and set particularly High
dagger in a different category but in
the broad sense of the term existential
I think we can apply it to both of these
men who have made an enormous in impact
on the thinking of 20th century Scholars
Heidegger was born in 1889 and died in
sart was born in 1905 and died in 1980.
sart very much like kierkegger guard
combined literary Gifts of great
extraordinary genius with a technical
grasp of some of the deepest questions
of abstract philosophy and sort was
famous for publishing his plays such as
and his his fictional works like the
Flies and the drama no exit and other
works of that type but his greatest
philosophical contribution is in his
large work entitled being
and nothingness
of course of course sart's
existentialism is a world apart from
that of Kierkegaard where kekergaard was
religious theistic and Christian
sard of course was vehemently opposed to
Christianity and to all forms of theism
and his existentialism may be defined in
terms of atheistic existentialism
he was the most important voice of
post-world War II Europe you remember
that in the 19th century there was an
unbridled Spirit of optimism where
people believed that through education
and through the Scientific Revolution
that the world was getting better and
better and that people were learning how
to control their own destiny how to feed
themselves how to fend for themselves
and how to avoid the problems of warfare
and relatively speaking the 19th century
was a rather peaceful time in world
history
but the bubble burst on the optimism of
the naive humanism of the 19th century
with the outbreak of World War One
but even then there were those who held
tenaciously to their Spirit of optimism
saying that world war one was the war to
end all wars the last great conflict
among people of a civilized sort
but that optimism was buried in the
death camps of World War II and the
revealing of the extent of the Holocaust
after World War II with the death camps
in Auschwitz and buchenwald and so on
bergen-belsen and those things coming to
light in modern Europe led to an
overwhelming almost tactile sense of
Despair among thinking people
and it was
transported to this country with people
like Jack Kerouac and others and the
Beat Generation who brought this this
philosophy of Despair to our culture
that was picked up and employed in drama
in the novel in popular music in and
through all of the Arts as
existentialism with its mood of Despair
swept across the landscape of America
having been imported from Western Europe
it's sart who gave the initial formula
for modern existentialism in which he
uses the phrase being translated
existence precedes
essence
and I think that really his thinking
goes beyond this idea that not only do
his existence first in the order of
knowing which would simply put him in
the same category of any empiricist the
going all the way back to somebody like
heraclitus who says you have becoming
rather than being and you have
particulars rather than universals and
things of that sort but really what what
sart is getting at is that existence
individual concrete human existence
precludes Essence there is no such thing
as mankind there's only men and women
there are no universals only the
particular concrete data of existence
and because there is no overarching
universal truth
that means there is nothing to unify our
understanding of reality
and in the final analysis reality itself
is absurd and irrational and nothing
really fits together in any meaningful
way so you have another kind another
form of nihilism following in the
footsteps of Nietzsche in the thinking
of Jean-Paul Sartre now when he looks at
human existence
he says that defining trait or
characteristic of a human being is
subjectivity
that we are subjects
not objects
and the chief attribute of a subject
is the subject's will
and specifically is free will
for without the Power of Choice without
the ability to make decisions for
oneself a person is not truly free and
if a person is not truly free then that
person
is not human he's not a subject as it
were
and so anything for sart that threatens
the subjectivity of human existence has
to go
and of course the greatest threat to
humanness that sart encountered in his
thinking was theism in general and
judeo-christianity in particular
because one of the great tenets of
Christian thought and judeo-christian
thought is the sovereignty of God and
for sort if God is sovereignty if God is
Sovereign truly sovereign
than man in the final analysis cannot be
free
because true Freedom according to sart
demands autonomy
that we be a law unto ourselves the
authentic existential person just as it
was with Nietzsche is a person who rules
himself he is subject to the rule of no
one or nothing else and if there's
anyone or anything that restricts to any
degree the freedom of that individual
then true Freedom has been lost and so
if man is truly free God cannot exist
his other argument against the existence
of God
is somewhat unique although uniqueness
doesn't admit to degrees it's just
extraordinarily unusual and he comes at
it this way
he said if the god of the Bible is true
and he's not only Sovereign and
omnipotent but he is omniscient that is
he knows everything he knows your
thoughts as you think them and before
you think to me he sees you're sitting
down and you're standing up he knows you
all together
if that is true that would destroy
Humanity because remember for sort
the essential although I hesitate to use
the word essence at all here but the
chief and most necessary attribute or
characteristic of a human being is
subjectivity
and if God is all seeing and all-knowing
then every human being would always be
constantly under the scrutiny
of God
and he talks about God in this sense as
being like a cosmic voyeur who is
looking through the keyhole into a
closed room and before his gaze
everything and everyone in the room is
laid bare
and that stare of God would dehumanize a
person because under the Gaze of God you
would be reduced to the status of object
rather than subject and he goes on to
these brilliant vignettes of insight
drawn from Human Experience he talks for
example
about uh the impropriety of staring at
human beings the way we stare at
paintings in a museum where you sit on a
bench across from the painting and you
just sit there and gaze at it for
minutes and perhaps even hours on end or
when you go to a zoo
and you see the monkeys in the cage then
you stand there and stare at them that
you wouldn't do that to real live people
because if you just went up to somebody
on the street and started to peer at
them intently and stare them at them
they would interpret that as a hostile
action which indeed indeed it would be
because you would be bearing them
reducing them to an object under your
scrutiny
he talks about the existential
experience of what he calls
existential self-awareness he used to
habituate the cafes on the Left Bank of
Paris and he talks about sitting at a
cafe table by himself one day
drinking coffee
and somebody else another Patron came in
and sat in a corner of the cafe behind
sart and sart then said that he sensed
could feel
the person's eyes on him and he turned
around and caught the person staring at
him
he said that was dehumanizing in fact
this makes up the final pages of the
drama no exit where in the final scene
people are in hell and all they're doing
is staring at each other and the punch
line is hell is other people
that is his
identity as a person he wanted to be
free to determine for himself and not be
fit or forced into some collective
category where he became a thing rather
than a person
but all this effort to achieve freedom
and subjectivity nevertheless for sart
was in the final analysis and exercise
and futility because he said that man in
the final analysis is a useless
fashion
see there's that word passion again and
he was an existentialist in the sense
that he was passionately concerned for
life and so on but all of that concern
and all of that passion and care that we
give to human existence in the final
analysis is an exercise in futility it
is useless
and one of the most morbid works that he
published was a real little book with
the one word title and the title was
nausea
that was his final
judgment on the meaning of human
existence
well in many ways Heidegger shared the
same pessimistic view of human existence
in his younger years Martin Heidegger uh
became
I wasn't all that young but
he became for a while a member of the
Nazi party he soon quit that and turned
his attention to his academic Pursuits
into his teaching
his most important work was entitled
sign on zeit
Being and Time notice that sart's main
book was being and nothingness
and for Heidegger it was being and time
both of them profoundly concerned with
the question of ontology what it means
to be and yet both of them rejecting the
classical categories of being and siding
on the side of becoming
he said that it is improper
to speak
of human beings simply by referring to
the concept of being which in German is
the word Psy
he said that man whatever else he is is
always
not sign but do sign
and what does that mean
to say that man is Dawson he takes the
uh
the spatial reference word da which
means there
there in that place
and attaches it to the German word for
being
so that da sign means literally being
there
I was driving home from church the other
day and my wife said
why are you going in this direction uh
is is are you going to be able to find
where we're headed
and I said well yes I think it's down
here and she said well everything
has to be somewhere
that's true and that's why men won't
stop and ask for directions because they
know that wherever they are they're
somewhere and wherever they're going has
to be somewhere and not only that but
what defines our human existence is that
we're not infinite and eternal we are
always in a particular place at a
particular time
you are not just being in general you
are being there you are where you are at
this moment I always do the trick
question with my students and ask them
where do they live and they'll tell me
some place 50 miles from where we're
talking about I said are you there now
and they say no I said well are you
alive now and they say yes and I said
well then that's not where you live
where you live is where you are that may
be your residence 50 miles from here or
where your house is but where you live
is where you are at the moment now the
whole point here is that our existence
is defined by our finite limits as
creatures
and this creates a sense of fear
of anxiety
of care what the German existentialist
called bazorgan a profound sense of
caring
an angst anxiety
in so far as we find ourselves
in a particular place at a particular
time and what makes it all the more
Dreadful is that how we experience this
sense of Dos sign or of being there
for high dagger he uses a German term
that uses the past participle form of a
verb and the word that he uses to Define
human existence and that which produces
anxiety and care
is the German word gevorfenheit
now the word gevorfenheit means
literally
having been thrown
having been thrown when I used to live
in the Netherlands
and learn the Dutch language which is a
cognate language to German
I've played baseball over there and we
had a star picture
on our team who was voted the best
pitcher in Europe
and the Dutch word for picture is very
w-e-r-p-e-r
and one of the things that I liked about
that was that he wasn't called a Hoyer a
thrower we make a distinction in
American baseball between pitchers who
were throwers and those who were
pitchers a pitcher is one who is under
control the other guy is just throwing
the ball and who knows where it's going
to go I wish that would help us
understand gevorfenheit but really what
what uh Heidegger has in view here is
more like a thrower than a veraper
governorfenheit means a sense of having
been hurled or thrown into existence you
didn't choose to be born where you were
born you didn't choose the parents that
you have or the culture in which you
live you experience a sense of having
simply been hurled into time and hurled
in the space chaotically for no purpose
and no great reason you're simply there
and that's what defines the struggle and
the passion of human existence that here
you are
here I am
I don't know where I came from I don't
know where I'm going I'm just sort of
hanging out here suspended in some kind
of Animation where I have all these
cares all these concerns all these
passions but there's no reason for my
being where I am at this given time and
so he ends pretty much with sart in the
philosophy of despair
one of their other compatriot was Albert
Camus who's famous for his
popularization of these thoughts in his
famous work the plague
and it was Camus who reflecting on these
same ideas of sart and high dagger who
said that there's only one serious
question left for philosophers to
explore
and that's the question of suicide
you see the real existential question
for one who experiences gevorfenheit is
the question posed by Hamlet to be
or not to be
that is the question whether it is Noble
in the mind to suffer the slings and
arrows of Outrageous Fortune that is
whether it's a virtuous and good and
reasonable thing to continue to endure
the sufferings that are imposed Upon Us
by fortuitous circumstances that in the
final analysis or outrageous
or says Hamlet what
by opposing
end them
what's he contemplating
he's contemplating suicide to die to
sleep per chance to dream
ah there's the rub for What Dreams May
Come in the sleep of death when we have
shuffled off this Mortal coil must give
us pause there's the respect that makes
Calamity of such long life
and so on and then he contemplates the
possibility of judgment after the grave
that gives him pause
but that's the question that's that
Camus following sort and high dagger say
is the question do I continue to bear
this pain in this world of Despair where
I have been hurled chaotically into
space and time
or do I take the initiative and end it
perhaps the greatest exponent of this in
popular literature was Ernest Hemingway
he said the only Power I have over death
is
to determine the way the place and the
time of my own death which he
methodically carried out by aiming his
best and most accurate hunting rifle at
his own head and set the trigger and
pulled the trigger and ended his life
fulfilling
the philosophy of despair